I don't know you very well but I suspect
you open your bananas from the wrong end
the reason for that supposition is that
virtually everybody who grows up in the
temperate zone does open them from the
wrong end I know I did until last week I
raised the point because I think it
tells us something interesting about
humanity we think of ourselves as
intelligent creative skeptical and we
often are but it is also possible for us
to take cultural information for example
which end to open the banana and to
accept it and to go a full lifetime
never questioning whether it might be
easier whether we might be holding it
the wrong way up and I think climate
change is a bit like this were we able
to peer into our various possible
futures I think we would come to
recognize the trajectory we're on as
much more frightening than we know and
the possibility of retooling society is
much more enticing much more interesting
the possibility to live through
something like an Enlightenment I'm an
evolutionary theorist what I do and what
I'm going to do here is provide
something akin to a map at the end you
should be able to read four things on
that map the first is where we are the
second is where we will end up if we do
nothing the third is where we should be
headed and the fourth is the minimum
conditions necessary to change in order
to get on that trajectory now I'm sure
I've raised some questions amongst many
of you why isn't evolutionary theorist
talking about climate change it's not as
if the climate evolves in the Darwinian
sense and that's true but I'm going to
argue that climate change is not really
a problem it's more a symptom of a
problem a problem that caused the
financial collapse of 2008 caused the
Deepwater Horizon oil spill in the Gulf
in 2010 and the ongoing Fukushima
disaster starting in March of 2011 if we
don't understand the connection between
these events then we are liable to reach
for the wrong solutions at best those
solutions will be ineffective at worst
they may even be harmful now
my contention that evolution has
something to do with this puzzle
involves the claim that there is
cultural evolution affecting markets
which is in and of itself not a
particularly radical argument there is
after all a fledgling field called
evolutionary economics that proceeds
roughly from that premise but those
attempts to map evolutionary theory on
to economics tend to proceed from the
economic side and they often miss
something about the Darwinian subtleties
that might be included if they came from
the biological side so the most
important thing we can do here today is
get the mapping correct so that we can
understand the implications there are
four necessary and sufficient conditions
to produce adaptive evolution of the
Darwinian type they are hierarchical
each one depends on the ones above they
are reproduction variation between the
products of reproduction heritability of
those variants and differential success
amongst them any system that has those
things will adaptively evolve whether it
is algorithms in a virtual environment
or whether it is rabbits on a prairie so
the question is how can those things
function in the economic context the
temptation is to imagine that agents
within the market people or companies
evolve within the ecosystem that is
provided by the market and I see two
failures there the first is that those
agents companies and individuals don't
really reproduce and that calls into
question all four of these criteria I
would argue instead that we should look
at strategies evolving culturally within
the market the strategies really
reproduce they do let me give you an
example
the Xerox Corporation innovated a
graphical user interface driven by Mouse
the Apple Corporation adopted that and
enhanced it they built up the metaphor
and made it more useful the Microsoft
Corporation took apples graphical user
interface and they broadened it by
making it run on a wider variety of
machines so you have reproduction
heritable variation and differential
success and in that context we could
imagine that the ecosystem in which
those strategies used by agents evolve
is
market but what we need to understand in
order to see this puzzle is that the
boundaries of the evolutionary
environment do not stop at the markets
edge what do we make of the company that
innovates a strategy of persuading the
legislature to give up a subsidy for
some sort of activity now if that
activity is useless or harmful we may
find that activity and athma but from a
Darwinian perspective it's every bit as
much a strategy as the graphical user
interface so my contention is strategies
evolve within markets and their larger
regulatory context in the story I've
told you with the graphical user
interface we see a classic tale of
enhanced utility where the pie grows as
the result of some sort of an insight
and that's a very positive thing that is
what is classically imagined to produce
profits in a market there are many
examples here we have the first step on
the road that eventually led to the
modern bicycle this is the dandy horse
of 1817 its originally imagined as an
aid to walking and it's practically
useless this is the uncomfortable and
difficult to control Boneshaker of 1869
this is the useful but very dangerous
penny farthing and finally in 1885 we
get the emergence of the safety bicycle
and it is fantastic it is so fantastic
in fact that it is the reason that the
GAE 1890s are gay this machine allows
people to travel five times as far five
times as fast under their only or under
their own power
it is the horseless horse so when we
look at this thing we can see the
classic trajectory of insight after
insight built up in the bicycle and we
can say oh that's how the market is
supposed to work that's how these
strategies are supposed to evolve but we
can also recognize in the bicycle
industry some other patterns the bicycle
industry causes itself a problem almost
immediately with the safety bicycle
which is that once you know how to
organize the parts once you know what
the shape of the frame is supposed to be
it becomes relatively easy to produce a
machine that is durable very useful
cheap and lasts forever
so even when bicycling becomes very
popular the bicycle industry can be kind
of sleepy
so the bicycle industry has had many
innovations since 1885 many of them are
important but it's also had long periods
of the doldrums when it had to monkey
around with gimmicks to sell people
things they didn't really need in order
to keep itself alive in the last 20
years it has begun monkeying around with
replacing the steel bicycle frame with
materials that are extremely expensive
and very fragile thus creating something
like a disposable bicycle this might be
funny if it didn't produce very serious
impacts every so often one of these
bicycles falls apart when somebody is
riding at a high speed and that's
obviously a severe danger so this is not
a case of a increase in utility again on
the size of the pie it's the opposite
case it's the case of a decrease in the
size of a pie where individuals may have
their slice grow but at some cost to us
all this is what all of our
environmental problems look like they
look like somebody making a profit for
degrading what belongs to the rest of us
it's quite clear that this behavior
should not be allowed within a
marketplace
we are fracturing the world we are
liquidating it we are draining it we are
diluting it we are over exploiting it it
is apparent to anyone who looks at what
we're up to the idea that this should
not be allowed is transparent my
eight-year-old son gets it immediately
my six-year-old son gets it in a matter
of a minute or two my cat is still stuck
on the idea that harm is a bad thing but
that's on him
nonetheless we have to ask ourselves
what fraction of the economic activity
that surrounds us is profitable only by
virtue of the fact that those who make
the money are externalizing the cost to
somebody else if we were to eliminate
such behaviors we would presumably
reduce the amount of activity a lot
which frightens people but we would
reduce it by exactly the fraction of
activities that shouldn't have existed
in the first place there's also some
question as to how we should feel about
when a corporation does something like
this
our initial instinct as human beings is
to be incensed incensed that somebody
has delivered a cost to somebody else
that didn't naturally belong to them but
I would argue that something of a
mistake the agents in the market are
responding to opportunities that we have
left open it makes no more sense to be
angry at them for exploiting profitable
opportunities than it does to be angry
at the mosquito for sucking your blood
the opportunity is there and if you
don't want the mosquito to suck your
blood you have to close down the
opportunity so let's look at a thought
experiment about how evolution of
strategies in markets would function on
the left you have a benevolent
corporation it does only what's in the
public's interest in the middle you have
a ruthless corporation that does only
what's in its own interest irrespective
of the cost of society and on the right
you have a corporation that's more
realistic it's a mixed strategy there
are some costs that will inflict on the
public there are some costs that go too
far and it tries to balance those
concerns
now imagine that these companies face a
series of choices across a year
occasionally those choices will make
what's good for society exactly the same
as what is good for the company in which
case what we get is no competitive
advantage they're dead even in
competition but most choices aren't
going to look like that there will be
equally rare ones in which what's good
for society is exactly the opposite of
what is good for the company in which
case only the ruthless corporation can
profit from the opportunity but the
common case will be somewhere in between
and in this case we see why evolution in
the market is producing some of the
phenomena we're experiencing in the case
that the what is good for the company is
somewhat
different from what is good for society
the ruthless corporation has the
greatest advantage why because it can do
anything it wants and the corporation
that is bound by what's good for society
can't do anything the corporation that
tries to balance these concerns finds
that it competes best with the ruthless
corporation the more ruthless it becomes
and the outcome is predictable in the
end in sectors of our economy where
there is not a lot of room for utility
increasing innovations we see an
evolution towards ruthlessness that has
predictable consequences and that has
interacted with what I will claim is the
central flaw in our system and when I
say system I mean our global system with
the with the u.s. at its head what we
have here are feedback loops that
interact wealth that is made in the
market is capable of increasing one's
power over-regulation tower over
regulation allows increased opportunity
to make money in the market this is a
positive feedback loop that should scare
any engineer or biologist because
positive feedback loops that are not
bounded by some negative feedback force
are unstable they detonate they explode
in our case this feedback loop has
re-engineered our system cryptically and
turned it into an engine for the
concentration of wealth and power and
this is it has installed amongst an
unelected group of very powerful and
wealthy people effective veto power over
any attempt to change from the status
quo so many people I know from
experience can accept this logic when it
comes to corporations what happens
though when you try to explain that this
logic actually is not sensitive to scale
that it applies equally to nations and
even more troubling ly to people is that
the mind wants to rebel it doesn't want
to believe it but my contention is the
same forces at work for us as
individuals that when people hear about
climate change and the harms that it
does they very naturally want to do
something they want to limit their
contribution
that danger they want to restrain their
own behavior reduce their carbon
footprint but paradoxically the
individual in the market by spending
more for more responsible products is
actually reducing their influence on the
system and causing the system to evolve
more quickly in the direction of
ruthlessness now there I call this the
personal responsibility vortex it sucks
good people in and it has two logical
consequences the first is that we should
redirect any effort that we are tempted
to spend on personal responsibility
towards collective action towards
collective action that can restructure
the incentives that surround the market
so that we actually have a chance of
altering the behavior the second logical
consequence is that there are two types
of systems that we can have one type of
system the costs of sustaining the
system go to the benevolent that system
will inevitably evolve towards
ruthlessness and instability the
Converse system though one where the
costs of maintaining society go to the
ruthless evolves towards benevolence and
stability
whenever policy is in question we should
ask ourselves does the policy lead in
the direction of the one type or the
other if we want to rescue our system
we're going to have to do some radical
things the first thing we need to do is
we need to place a firewall that is
impermeable between the marketplace and
the regulatory apparatus it is no
problem that people make money in the
marketplace there is nothing wrong when
someone creates utility then being
rewarded for it the problem is when that
reward begins to generate its own
rewards positive feedback sets in the
second thing we have to do is we have to
rethink the way we keep track of
behavior in the marketplace we need full
cost accounting which means that every
cost that is generated by an activity in
the market needs to show up on the
balance sheet whether that is borrowing
from future generations whether it is
putting the population at risk
whatever the cost of an activity are be
they've military or otherwise they need
to be included in the price of the
product or otherwise returned to those
who decided to initiate the action if we
did that
the amount of economic activity would
drop but it would drop to exactly those
behaviors that are actually beneficial
to society leaving out all of those
externalities that are generating so
much profit with our current system now
I began this by saying that I thought we
would think very differently about
climate change if we could look at our
possible futures I also have a similar
sense about the past the sense is if we
could show the people who architected
our system the way the system would come
apart in the end they might have
protected us better the founding fathers
never saw a bicycle they probably
couldn't have imagined a chainsaw they
certainly could not have foreseen
hyaline logging mountaintop removal
mining they couldn't have imagined deep
ocean drilling if they had been able to
see those things
my guess is sustainability would have
been at the top of their list of
concerns I'm thinking it might even have
ended up as our first amendment in the
Bill of Rights how cool would it be if
our Bill of Rights went to 11 no really
how cool would it be if our Bill of
Rights went to 11 yes I think they would
have been very focused on sustainability
and reversibility unfortunately there is
no mechanism to deliver them the map
[Applause]